But not all uses were simple substitutions.
Some participants relied on what LLMs were good at, depending on what they picked up from the media, friends, or colleagues.
Nearly everyone used ChatGPT to paraphrase.
Using it for coding purposes was also widespread, justified by the idea that it's good at it, because they had heard that it had been trained on lots of code.
Yet for them, coding was mostly seen as a means to achieve a more valuable end.
It didn't need to be elegant.
It just needed to be functional.
Constance said she didn't care if her code was pretty or fast, only that it ran.
Tobias went further, rejecting the idea of coding as creative work.
I think for me, it's more like implementing something I've already set out.
I did my research design, so I kind of mapped out the process of data collection or data analysis.
It feels like I've already put the thought into how I wanted to do it, and then I just tell it, chat GPT, to implement.
Participants also built on the existing division of labor in their line of work to assign tasks to the LLM.
As such, researchers quickly sought to test the accuracy of literature reviews or bibliography management.
Yinxin found ChatGPT incredibly efficient, especially in the writing of quantitative social science essays, since they tend to be standard in format.
At the same time, Charlotte noticed that they're quite good when it comes to referencing with rigid guidelines.
So if there's something really clear, like a formula for how to do referencing, for example, it usually can do that.
Most agreed that LLMs performed best on standardized tasks governed by precise rules.
Over time, however, participants began to push beyond these obvious use cases.
In law, for instance, Alice realized that what she thought of as a single task was too unwieldy for the LLM.
What felt like one smooth action to her had to be broken into smaller, more manageable steps.
I think one of the key things to get proper results is really to dissect every part of what you want to reflect on and go step by step.
Because even if you give the big picture at the beginning and then try to break it down, it tends to try to do everything at once.
I mean, it was really confused.